Guide to the Kenneth Silverman Research Collection on Samuel F.B. Morse MC 173
New York University Archives
Kenneth Silverman Research Collection on Samuel F.B. Morse
1792-1892
MC 173
New York University Archives
6.0 linear feet
This collection contains research materials collected by Kenneth Silverman while working on his book Lightning Man: The Accursed Life of Samuel F.B. Morse. Materials include photocopied articles and essays, microfilm, and correspondence (mostly transcribed) dating from 1792 to 1892. This collection does not include original materials from Morse.
Silverman, Kenneth
Arrangement
Folders in Boxes 1-3 are arranged chronologically. Box 4 is arranged alphabetically by topic. Boxes 5 and 6 are arranged by document type.
The files are grouped into four series.
Chronological Files
Subject File/Index and Other Papers
Articles, Depositions, and Electronic Materials
Microfilm
Scope and Contents
This collection includes photocopied articles and essays, microfilm, correspondence (mostly transcribed) and other research materials. The dates range from 1792-1892. The folders in the collection are arranged chronologically and by subject.
Historical/Biographical Note
Kenneth Silverman currently serves as professor emeritus of English at New York University. He is the author of several biographies, including those of Samuel Morse, Cotton Mather, and Edgar Allen Poe. The Life and Times of Cotton Mather, perhaps his best-known work, won both the Bancroft Prize in History and a Pulitzer Prize for Biography. Silverman is also a member of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences.
Samuel F.B. Morse, noted artist and inventor, served as a professor of painting and sculpture at New York University. In 1838, he perfected his most famous invention, the telegraph.
Sources:
All biographic information about Kenneth Silverman from the NYU website.
Dim, Joan Marans, and Nancy Murphy Cricco. The Miracle on Washington Square: New York University. Lanham: Lexington, 2001.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions. This collection is in
off-site storage
.
Morse, Samuel Finley Breese, 1791-1872; Silverman, Kenneth; Articles.; Correspondence.; Essays.; Federal government records.; Microfilms.
- Series I: Chronological Files
  - Chronological File, 1792-1811 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Barcode #: 3 1142 042257868
  - Chronological File, 1812-1815 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225786 8
  - Chronological File, 1816-1818 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chronological File, 1819-1824 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chronological File, 1825-1827 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chronological File, 1828-1830 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chronological File, 1831-1833 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chronological File, 1834-1836 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Chronological File, 1837 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Chronological File, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Chronological File, 1839 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Chronological File, 1840 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Chronological File, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Chronological File, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Chronological File, 1843 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Chronological File, 1844 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Chronological File, 1844 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Chronological File, 1845 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225787 6
  - Chronological File, 1845 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Chronological File, 1846 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Chronological File, 1846 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Chronological File, 1847 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Chronological File, 1847 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Chronological File, 1848 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Chronological File, 1848 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Chronological File, 1848 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Chronological File, 1849 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Chronological File, 1849 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Chronological File, 1849 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Chronological File, 1850 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Chronological File, 1850 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Chronological File, 1850 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Chronological File, 1851 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Chronological File, 1852 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225788 4
  - Chronological File, 1852 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Chronological File, 1853 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Chronological File, 1854 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Chronological File, 1854 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Chronological File, 1855 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Chronological File, 1855 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Chronological File, 1856 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Chronological File, 1857 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Chronological File, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Chronological File, 1859 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Chronological File, 1860 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Chronological File, 1861-1862 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Chronological File, 1863-1864 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Chronological File, 1865-1866 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Chronological File, 1867-1868 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Chronological File, 1869-1870 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Chronological File, 1871-1872 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Series II: Subject File/Index and Other Papers
  - Subject Index/Number Key, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225790 0
  - A-B, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - C (1), undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - C (2), undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - D-H, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - I-L, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - M, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - N, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - O-R, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - S, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - T, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - U-Z, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Undated miscellaneous materials (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Cornell Papers, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Morse Centennial 1944, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Mullaly, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Patents, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Translations, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Series III: Articles, Depositions, and Electronic Materials
  - Articles (1), undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225789 2
  - Articles (2), undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Articles (3), undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Articles (4), undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Articles (5), undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Undated miscellanous materials (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - 1852 Deposition, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Zip Disk of Notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Series IV: Microfilm
  - The Papers of Samuel F.B. Morse (LC MSS 16, 372: Reels 1-35), undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225791 8
  - Samuel F.B. Morse and Other Members of the Morse and Walker Families, 1861-1869 (LC MSS 6295 A), undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Jedidiah Morse Papers (N-YHS: Misc. Reel # 10--negative only), undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Amos Kendall (LC MSS 17, 664: Reels 1-3), undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - History of Science (Early American Telegraph Companies, pamphlets, 1845-1861; Morse, S.F.B., Examination of the Telegraphic Apparatus, 1869; Morse's Patent by Kendall), undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Edward Julian Nally Papers (Box 12), undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Goldsmiths' Kress Library of Economic Literature (Alfred Voil, The American Electro-Magnetic Telegraph, 1845; Description of the American Electro-Magnetic Telegraph, 1845), undated (Box 6, Folder 7)